hi everyone today we'll be creating a shader
for an animated glowing material in unity
this is great for glowing objects especially
in dark lighting as this material was created
for a group project called terminus a tower
defense game where you have to prevent viruses
from breaching the firewall you can see the
animated material in use of the play area
so let's get started on the shader
unity i've already set up two objects
with the basic unity material which will
be changed to our customer down the line
first off create a standard surface
shader and rename it to standard emissive
we're going to be using this
to render the base material
the top line here tells you where is the
shadow located right now it's located under
the custom tab but if you want you can choose
where it's located by changing this string
i'm going to remove the front custom so it will
appear directly in the drop-down list instead
we can also see that in the current material there
are already some default properties that we set up
for us however we donate all of them so commented
the glossiness and metallic properties including
all the references to them we also won't be
needing the unity instancing support either
instead what we do need to add other unity
pbs lighting for physically based shading
random queue of geometry under the substituted
text since we're working with an opaque object
with those setup let's start working on the
properties we're going to start by renaming
main texture to albedo and adding
in an additional alpha a to its name
this is left as 2d as a 2d texture
rename all the references of main texture to
albedo 2. to make the references clearer under
void surf we're also going to rename c to albedo
at the same time shift the color to here instead
if you have worked with 3d objects before you
might know that there are other textures that
are added to make the object look more realistic
so we are also going to add two more properties
normal and mass map textures normal maps
handle the bumps and dense of a 3d material
as for massmap it's quite different
from the rest of the textures
remember recommended glossiness amateur properties
last minute has it covered the different channels
rgba that makes up the mask represents metallic
occlusion detail mask and smoothness respectively
essentially combining four textures into one
you can also put any of these individual textures
into this slot and it will still work perfectly
fine however if you want to include two or
more of these but do not have a mask map
then you need to have them listed
as individual properties instead
like this next call the type of data
for each property under the subshader
to have them show up in the random material
copy and paste this line for albedo texture
and change the property name to advancement do
this for normal too but you need to fix 3 instead
also put the texture inside the unpacked
scale normal function to unpack the map
with a scale of 1. below it assign the output
o with the properties so all.normal is normal
for mass map as mentioned before assign a
different channels to their respective texture
whilst map r for metallic g for occlusion
b for detail mask and a for smoothness
however we don't need the detail mask since that
is only required for very close-up details of
the object here's also where if you have created
individual channels for any of these properties
reference them here instead of
mass map going back to unity
you can see the properties have been
updated with the ones we wrote and in
all the textures and you should be able to
see that the material is working properly
so now we're going to move on to the exciting
part making this material glow and animated
the glow as you might have guessed is handled
by emission just like a normal standard material
however we're going to make it pulse so that
it looks more organic and admission for the
texture emission color for the color of
the emission and emission intensity for
the base brightness of the emission these three
properties are also found in the normal material
for the pulsing we need two more float values
emission glow for heartbreak to glow and pulsing
and emission glue duration for how long is
one cycle of the pulse for now let's set the
default amount to 1 for the glows and 5 seconds
for the duration as usual write this down here
and add in the fix 4 for emission for the
output we're going to write a formula this
is to get the color emission texture which is
then multiplied by the strength of emission this
part is in brackets and is where we are going
to control the pulsing emission intensity for
the base intensity plus the additional glow
that is added to the base intensity based on
two things the time since the level has been
loaded and the duration of the glow cycle
we are also using absolute here so that
the resulting glow would never be lower
than the base intensity let's see this in action
to make the housing more obvious you can
either increase the intensity or the glow
based on what you need now we're going to create
a new shader but this time it's an unlit shader
we're going to copy some of these components
into our shader to create the passing animation
so that not all parts of the texture will
glow uniformly copy everything underpass
and paste it here so that you render
the surface shader before this
also add in the tag render type fade which will
utilize the transparency value from the texture
that is rendered here to create an overlay on
the base material at the same time add zero
on for writing to the buffer and blend this
color zero for multiplicative blending time
once again renaming texture to
scrolling mask for all the references
and create a property for this
under the properties section
before proceeding further for the code let's make
the overlay texture first open up photoshop or any
drawing surface that you have and create
a new canvas of 1 0 2 4 x 1 0 2 4 pixels
right click the paint bucket tool and you will
see this this is the gradient tool but first
let me backtrack slightly transparency value is
determined based on the grayscale of the texture
with black being opaque and white being
transparent thus as we want the ingredient
for the illumination we need the texture to
have a gradient going from darker gray or black
to white so open up the color picker and then
the two ends pick a darker shade i'm going
with dark gray so that the dimmer section of the
material will still have a cycle coming through
at the center make it white while holding
shift when you drag your mouse down to from
the top to the bottom you have this
beautiful gradient save this as a png
not by immunity add this to the material and
you'll be able to faintly see the gradient overlay
now time to make this overlay move
back here create two more float properties called
scroll x and scroll y with a default value of 0.2
and then i'm here too
next under fragment we're going
to move the uv of the texture by
multiplying time dot y before scroll
values and then adding it to the uv
so yeah i hope you enjoyed and
there we go the shader is complete
let's take a look at our final product